<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The excise-mens lamentation: or, an impeachment in behalf of the Commons of this nation, against their insulting publicans, and cruell oppressors and extortioners: with their acknowledgment, confession, and testimony, touching their proceedings in each county; and the vast and mighty summes vvich they most wickedly retained: collected by their unlimited power, spungie hearts, and long-stretched consciences. Also, the rising of the Welch-men against a party of them at Monmouth; and the manner how Mr. Crow (the farmer of excise) ran naked into a tub of feathers; where, after a short time, he was taken, and a great oath and charge inflicted upon him. Published for information of the people.</title>
            <title>Excise-mens lamentation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E683_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206812</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865918</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865918</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84283)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166372)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E683[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The excise-mens lamentation: or, an impeachment in behalf of the Commons of this nation, against their insulting publicans, and cruell oppressors and extortioners: with their acknowledgment, confession, and testimony, touching their proceedings in each county; and the vast and mighty summes vvich they most wickedly retained: collected by their unlimited power, spungie hearts, and long-stretched consciences. Also, the rising of the Welch-men against a party of them at Monmouth; and the manner how Mr. Crow (the farmer of excise) ran naked into a tub of feathers; where, after a short time, he was taken, and a great oath and charge inflicted upon him. Published for information of the people.</title>
                  <title>Excise-mens lamentation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for G. Horton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Taxation --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Excise tax --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Confiscations and contributions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166372:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EXCISE-MENS LAMENTATION: OR, An Impeachment in behalf of the Comons of this Nation, againſt their inſulting Publicans, and cruell Oppreſſors and Extortioners: With their Acknowledgment, Confeſſion, and Teſtimony, touching their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in each County;</p>
            <p>And the vaſt and mighty Summes vvhich they moſt wickedly retained: Collected by their unlimitted Power, Spungie Hearts, and long-ſtretched Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the riſing of the Welch-men againſt a party of them at Monmouth; and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how Mr. CROW (the Farmer of Excize) ran naked into a Tub of feathers; where, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort time, he was taken, and a great Oath and Charge inflicted upon Him.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for information of the People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Horton.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:166372:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166372:2"/>
            <head>THE EXCISE-MENS LAMENTATION: OR, Their ſtrange Creed, and Letany, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God the Father have mercy upon Us, miſerable Excize-men; for we have done thoſe things which we ought not to have done, and left undone thoſe things which we ought to have done, and there is no truth in Us; Lord pardon all our high, unjuſt, and illegal proceedings,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166372:3"/>and deal not with Us after our ſins, nor reward Us after our iniquities. And we beſeech thee Lord powr thy grace into our hearts, that as we have known Chriſt thy ſons incarnation by the meſſage of an Angel: ſo by his croſs and paſſion, we may be brought unto the glory of his reſurrection. But Lord, open thou our hearts, and let our purſes ſhew forth thy praiſe; that ſo we may with cheerfulneſſe and alacrity return and give in a moſt juſt and due account of all thoſe vaſt and great ſums, which we have wickedly, fraudulently, and deceitfully gained by an unlimited and out-ſtretched Conſcience; for we muſt ingenuouſly acknowledge and confeſs, that our carriage and proceedings hath been ſo high rigid and harſh both to the Rich and Poor, that with a wet finger we could eaſily cleer and lay up 500 l. per annum, whereas before this bleſſed Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we were not maſters of 50 pence at the yeares end: But alas! all theſe great and ill-gotten Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, after ſome time of Extortion, began to diſſolv and melt like ſnow in warm gleams: Therefore, we now earneſtly deſire to abandon thoſe ways of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs; humbly beſeeching the Lord to give us hearts to dread him, and for the time to come dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to live after his Commandements.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166372:3"/>
            <p> Yet notwithſtanding many there are who ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main very rigid and cruel to the Poor; and having lately put in practice their cruell proceedings at Monmouth, the poor people taking ball'd Time by the fore-lock, unanimouſly roſe, and fell upon he quarters of one Mr. Crow (the Farmer of Excize) beat off his guard, but he himſelf ecaped in his ſhirt, and ran and himſelf in a Tub of Feathers; but all would not ſave him; for at laſt he became a Bird in hand, and (contrary to his expectation) ſet him free with all his feathers; who having made him ſwear on the Bible, that he ſhould become an honeſt man, they diſmiſſed him without wounds, but half frighted him out of his wits.</p>
            <p>Others there are who take upon them the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Office; but mum! onely I ſay, if there muſt needs be a trade driven, and an imployment found for the pragmatique active hands of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, Let them even turn aſide to thoſe Publicans, and Extortioners, who have devoured Widowes houſes, and brought good families to a morſell of bread; O that the ſoldier may be reſolv'd the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is intollerable, and that the Commonalty may be confirmed where the Knave lies; for till this fair reckoning be made, it is impoſſible but there muſt be an inward core and grudg between man and man.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:166372:4"/>
            <p> O but let us conſider, when the Revenue of the Miniſtery is once taken off, what iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant piece of Homily, will venture the merchandiſe of his labour for an uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of bread? into what contempt and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal would that glorious calling crumble in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, when every Clodpate ſhal ſit in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether a Divine deſerve his Sunday dinner? Tis true indeed, ſuch pitiful ſhreds of predication as the world may produce, may preach through plain ſong to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of the Vulgar, and the people perhaps delight to have it ſo: but yet let me tell you 'twill be a doleful Meſſage, when judgments become their own Prophets, and the plagues of heaven find no fore runners of their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid preſence. O but theſe are times of revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and men are more familiar with the Deity then in the dayes of old! I grant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is abundance of pretended inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166372:4"/>with divine workings, elſe certainly the modern confidence were a ſtrange pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; but nevertheleſs (with ſubmiſſion to the ſupream cenſure) the Widow would hardly have found her groat by puting out the candle; neither we in ſlighting the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, which are the miniſteriall means of our illumination, ſhal ever by the feel of our groping invention be able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our ſtraying feet in the wayes of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, under the ridiculous notion of prophetical inſpiration; no, though we cut our ſelves with Knives, and cry mightily; for that Spirit may either be aſleep, or in a journy, or in purſuit; but reſolution brooks no counſel: nay, then we have no refuge but our tears and prayers; And happier then are the dead, that are already dead, then the living which are yet alive. Queſtionleſs, but there are tendet hearts, which would ſhow
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166372:5"/>the bowels of their compaſſion in healing up theſe Ulcers: yet if you would know the reaſon of this obſtruction, Saint Paul ſayes, There was a Law in his members warring againſt the Law of his mind, and bringing him into ſubjection to the Law of ſin and death: Therefore, ſince we have found the malady, let us endeavor to ſuppreſs its fury in the bud, every man mend one, and let the general prayers mediate for all; for man muſt die, and the good and evil of his Works follow him to his ſadder doom or happineſs; and then, my hearts,</p>
            <p>An honeſt Conſcience, Is worth a Common-Wealth.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
